He's a jew. He’s a Neo-Nazi. With one true enemy… Himself!
The Believer is a drama film directed by Henry Bean.
A hardcore US racist skinhead who, because of his intelligence, leads a gang dedicated to
fighting the enemy: the supposed American-Jewish conspiracy for domination.
However, he's hiding a secret: he's Jewish-born, a brilliant scholar whose questioning of the tenets of his faith has
left him angry and confused, turning against those who he thinks have a tragic history of their own making.
Danny Balint, played by Ryan Gosling.
Carla Moebius, played by Summer Phoenix.
Lina Moebius, played by Theresa Russell.
Curtis Zampf, played by Billy Zane.
Billings, played by Garret Dillahunt.
Guy Danielsen, played by A.D. Miles.
The Believer is a 2001 American drama film written and directed by Henry Bean in his
feature directorial debut, based on a story by Bean and Mark Jacobson.
Starring Ryan Gosling, Billy Zane, Theresa Russell, and Summer Phoenix, the
film follows Daniel Balint, a Jew who becomes a neo-Nazi.
The film is loosely based on the true story of Dan Burros, a member of the American Nazi Party and the New York branch of the
United Klans of America who died by suicide after being revealed as Jewish by a reporter from The New York Times.
The Believer premiered at the Sundance Film Festival on January
19, 2001, where it won the Grand Jury Prize.
It was theatrically released in the United States on May 17, 2002, to
positive reviews, with particular praise for Gosling's performance.
The film earned several accolades, including the Golden St.
George at the 23rd Moscow International Film Festival.
It received four nominations at the 17th Independent Spirit Awards, Best First Feature and Best
Screenplay for Bean, Best Male Lead for Gosling, and Best Supporting Female for Summer Phoenix.
The film explores themes of new york city,
neo-nazism, antisemitism, bigotry, hatred.
The tone is emotional.